Today's דף Daf is מ"א. Mem Aleph. We pick up at the
bottom of מ' עמוד ב'. Mem Amud Bet. And we
are where are we? Okay.
תא
שמע.
Ta Shma.
It's six lines from the bottom, middle of the line, right near
where the פסוק Pasuk is, right near the circle. So again to
remind you what we're doing, we are having this question
about whether the הגרלה Hagralah is מעכב Me'akev or
not, whether the actual drawing of lots prevents the ceremony from being
acceptable. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says the whole pairing isn't מעכב, Me'akev,
right? And that was the חידוש Chiddush of רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon
position that רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon position was that based on, thank
you, based on as we pointed out yesterday, based on the way
he reads the פסוק Pasuk about יעמד חי לפני ה' לכפר עליו,
Yaamad Chai Lifnei Hashem Lechaper Alav, the way תוספות Tosafot understands it,
that actually he does not link, he says for the שעיר המשתלח
Se'ir Hamishtaleach to be good you have to do what you need
to do for the שעיר המשתלח, Se'ir Hamishtaleach, but it's not linked
to what happens to the other שעיר. Se'ir. And therefore for him
you don't even need to do the whole בדיעבד, Bedi'avad, you don't
even need to do the whole pairing, you don't have to do
anything. But that's רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. According to everyone else, of
course you have to do the pairing and what not, but do
you have to בדיעבד Bedi'avad do the lottery? Let's say you just
designated verbally without doing the lottery. This is being debated in the
גמרא Gemara between רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai
and to some degree it's maybe connected to the debate of רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah about other things whether
they're מעכב Me'akev or not, or נחמיה Nechemya whether order is מעכב.
Me'akev. So that's the question whether the הגרלה Hagralah is מעכב. Me'akev.
Let's take a look at where this goes. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this:
תא שמע, Ta Shma, come in
here, ועשהו
חטאת. Ve'asahu Chatat. הגורל עושהו חטאת ואין השם עושהו חטאת. Hagoral oseo
chatat ve'ein hashem oseo chatat. So it says what's the פסוק? Pasuk?
The
פסוק Pasuk is אשר עלה עליו הגורל לה' ועשהו חטאת. Asher alah
alav hagoral l'Hashem ve'asahu chatat. So how do you read ועשהו חטאת?
Ve'asahu Chatat? You could read ועשהו חטאת Ve'asahu Chatat maybe means and
then you שחט Shechted as חטאת. Chatat. Or if you want to
read about designation, it could be God's name was עלה עליו, Alah
alav, and then he makes it a חטאת, Chatat, maybe he designates
it, maybe he declares it as a חטאת, Chatat, which would mean
the גורל Goral doesn't make it a חטאת. Chatat. The ברייתא Brayta
here is learning ועשהו Ve'asahu means אשר עלה עליו הגורל לה' ועשהו
Asher alah alav hagoral l'Hashem ve'asahu
and the גורל Goral had made it into a חטאת. Chatat. And
that's how it's reading the פסוק. Pasuk. Not that Aaron will ועשהו
חטאת, Ve'asahu Chatat, but the גורל Goral אשר עלה עליו הגורל לה'
ועשהו Asher alah alav hagoral l'Hashem ve'asahu and the גורל Goral had
made it into a חטאת. Chatat.
Because for the גורל Goral had made...
exactly, it's like for.
Right, exactly. For the גורל Goral had already made it a חטאת.
Chatat.
Right, or the גורל Goral which you know, which the גורל Goral
had fallen upon it and had made it into a חטאת. Chatat.
Okay, ועשהו חטאת. Ve'asahu Chatat. So that's the way it's reading:
הגורל עושהו חטאת ואין השם עושהו חטאת. Hagoral oseo chatat ve'ein hashem
oseo chatat. So the גורל Goral makes it a חטאת Chatat and
not the name. Now the name could mean it says לה' חטאת,
L'Hashem Chatat, so the name of ה', Hashem, but it also means
not the designation. No verbal designation makes it into a חטאת, Chatat,
it is just the גורל Goral itself that makes it into a
חטאת. Chatat. Yes, but is the designation... yes, but there's no verbal
designation. It's the act of the גורל Goral having fallen on it.
What is the designation?
Yes, but there's no verbal designation. It's the act of the גורל
Goral having fallen on it.
Well let's take a look. Let's take a look as it continues.
Okay, שיכול והלא דין הוא. Sheyachol v'halo din hu.
I could have made a קל וחומר Kal vachomer that this should
work, that the designating of it without the גורל Goral should work.
ומה במקום שלא קידש הגורל, Uma bemakom shelo kidash hagoral, what's in
a place where the lots are not significant? You know normally, as
we're going to see, where would it anyway be a relevant scenario
of drawing lots on an animal? So the best, you know, you
could say well you make... you have two animals as a קרבן
Korban and you haven't said which is which. But that's like... why?
That's bizarre. So but there is a case where that happens, which
is birds. When you take a... the whole מסכת קינים Masechet Kinnim
is about taking two birds,
because a person particularly like at the end of a טהרה Tahara
process, a יולדת, Yoledet, a זב, Zav, מצורע, Metzora, etc., you take
two birds and one is an עולה Olah and one is a
חטאת. Chatat. And we're going to see in a minute that actually,
and this is a very strange הלכה Halacha by these, you don't
have to designate them at the beginning. You can take them as
a pair and the designation can come later. And that designation, and
we'll see when that occurs, comes through verbal designation. Okay so that's
going to be compared to this case which is through the drawing
of lots. So let's read this.
Yes, like a בכור, Bechor, right?
Where you sanctify... but that also is already קדוש מרחם. Kadosh meirechem.
You might do an additional you know sanctification.
But the גורל, Goral, I mean it has to be that one
because the גורל Goral fell on them, you can't sanctify the other
one.
All right, but okay, but that's—but the קידוש השם *Kiddush Hashem*—but it's
a בכור *bechor* even without the קידוש השם *Kiddush Hashem*.
There's something you can say about the בכור *bechor*. It's the same
thing. It's the—is the—it's the—one—this is the one לה' *Lashem* because
the גורל goral *goral* fell on it. Right? Well, we're contrasting it
to a case—but we're contrasting it to a case where verbal designation
is required and makes it a חטאת chatas *chatas* and a lottery
does not. If you did not designate, it's still a בכור *bechor*,
correct. It's a מצוה *mitzvah* to also sanctify it, but it's קדוש
*kadosh* even without a verbal designation. אלו כופיהו *Alu kopeinhu*. ומה במקום
שלא קידש הגורל קידש השם uma bimkom shelo kidesh hagoral kidesh hashem,
*Uma bimakom shelo kiddash hagoral kiddash hashem*, when the גורל goral *goral*
doesn't work, like by the case of the two birds, nevertheless the
designation works—so here you see שם *shem* means like the verbal designation—מקום
שקידש הגורל hagoral *Makom shekiddash hagoral*,
where the גורל goral *goral* does work, like by the goats, אינו
דין שיקדש השם eino din sheyekadesh hashem, *eino din sheyekaddesh hashem*? How
much more so should a verbal designation work? That's even better. You
directly, you know, verbally say this is a חטאת chatas, *chatas*. תלמוד
לומר *Talmud lomar*, ועשהו חטאת ve'asahu chatat, *ve'aso chatas*. No, the גורל
goral *goral* had made it into a חטאת chatas, *chatas*. הגורל hagoral
עושהו חטאת chatas ואין השם עושהו חטאת chatas. *Hagoral oso chatas ve'ein
hashem oso chatas*. Only the גורל *goral*, not the name. Now, that
is pretty clear because if you say the גורל *goral* is not
מעכב *me'akev*, how else are you going to determine which is the
חטאת chatas, *chatas* and which is the שעיר לה' *seir Lashem* and
which is the שעיר לעזאזל *seir La'azazel*? The only way you would
be able you would do it is through a verbal designation. And
this ברייתא Baraita *braita* is saying, sorry bud, verbal designation won't work,
you've got to do it through the drawing of lots. So if
that's true, clearly you need to draw lots, you don't have another
way of designating. So let's take a look. Now of course we
had discussed before, maybe this depends on רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* רבי
נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemiah*. Maybe, maybe this is, you know, maybe only רבי
נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemiah* who normally says things are מעכב *me'akev* would be
of this position. But now we're going to prove that it's even
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. סתם ספרא מני *Stam sifra mani*? Now this
is a ספרא *Sifra*. This is a תורת Toras כהנים kohanim *Torat
Kohanim*, the Tannaic commentary, you know, halakhic commentary on ויקרא *Vayikra*. And
that is סתם *stam*, it's not named. So the anonymous voice in
the ספרא *Sifra*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, מני *mani*? Is רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. We know by tradition that that is רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda*. He is the author of the ספרא *Sifra*. He's the
anonymous voice. So this is a רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* position. דקתני
*Dekatani*, הגורל hagoral עושהו חטאת chatas, ואין השם עושהו חטאת chatas, *hagoral
oso chatas ve'ein hashem oso chatas*. Only the drawing of lot, not
the verbal designation. אלמא הגרלה hagralah מעכבא *Alma hagrala me'akva*. You see
the drawing of lots is מעכבא *me'akva*. Because that is the only
way if, if you can't call, designate it, that won't work. The
only way you can do it is by drawing lots. You have
no other choice but to draw the lots. תיובתא דמאן דאמר הגרלה
hagralah? לא מעכבא תיובתא *Tyuvta deman d'amar hagrala lo me'akva tyuvta*. This
is an absolute contradiction to the one who says that the drawing
of lot does not—is not מעכב *me'akev*. And that's how the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* ends. So the end of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, although
we had ברייתות *braitas* before going both ways, because of this the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* ends conclusively that even the most extreme position, right,
even—there were questions whether is the debate in רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*,
is the debate in רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemiah*. But here the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* concludes that whether רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, whether רבי נחמיה
*Rabbi Nechemiah*, everybody would agree that the drawing of lot is מעכב
*me'akev*. Okay, and therefore, and that position wins out. However, even though,
even though as we pointed out—I'm going to say—even though as we
pointed out, it's not an עבודה avodah. *avoda*, right? You could do
it with a non-כהן Kohen *kohen*. I—the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen
Gadol*—כהן Kohen גדול *Kohen Gadol*'s left hand, doesn't have to be the
סגן sgan, *sgan*, could be the left hand. So again, it's pretty
interesting, something that's מעכב *me'akev* that's not designated as an עבודה avodah.
*avoda*.
And the other thing is to remember, yes, that according to רבי
שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*, not just is he—he would be—he's the outlier position.
He's the real like contrary voice. He's saying not only is the
drawing of lots not מעכב *me'akev*, the whole pairing of it is
also not מעכב *me'akev* and they're really independent they—בדיעבד bedieved, *bedi'avad*, לכתחילה
lechatchila *lechat'chila*
of course you do it, but בדיעבד bedieved *bedi'avad* they could be
independent of one another.
So what is it? A מצוה *mitzvah* of the כהונה *kehuna*?
It is a—it's a מצוה *mitzvah* of the עבודה avodah *avoda*. What
do you mean, according to רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*? Yeah.
According to רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. In other words, it's מעכב *me'akev*
but it's not an עבודה *avoda*.
It's not an עבודה *avoda* but it's a requirement of, you know—so
what exactly gets labeled
in the תרי"ג מצוות *taryag mitzvot*?
No, no, no, it's one of the פרטים *pratim* of how you
do the עבודת יום כיפורים *avodas Yom Kippurim*. But not every detail
is—now that raises the question, what is the significance of labeling something
an עבודה *avoda*? One significance of it is labeling it is whether
it requires a כהן Kohen *kohen*, or on יום כיפור Yom Kippur
*Yom Kippur* whether it requires a כהן Kohen גדול *Kohen Gadol*, whether
it's—needs to be done בימין *be'yamin*, right? You know, so there are
like certain—there are various הלכות *halakhot* about what are the consequences of
something being an עבודה *avoda*. But it's tricky because it gets to
the question of שחיטה shechitah. *shechita*. שחיטה shechitah, *shechita* doesn't need a
כהן *kohen*. Is שחיטה shechitah, *shechita* an עבודה *avoda* that's כשירה בזר
*kesheira be'zar* or is it not an עבודה *avoda*?
You know, so—somebody mentioned בגדים *bigadim* is not an עבודה *avoda* per
se.
That's a good example. And if you don't have the בגדים *bigadim*
on then the עבודה *avoda* is פסולה *pesula*. So washing the ידיים
רגליים *yadayim raglayim*, if you don't do it, the עבודה *avoda* is
פסולה *pesula*, but it's not an עבודה *avoda* per se. But exactly
what gets designated as an עבודה *avoda* is tricky. Is it like
a backwards—you know, a backwards designation, if we find out that you
need a כהן *kohen* and you need בימין *be'yamin*, then we're going
to call it an עבודה *avoda*? Or is it, you know, some
other thing?
Like is it a הכשר מצוה *hechsher mitzvah*?
Right, so it's right, so something along those lines, you know. All
right, anyways, that is—it's a larger conversation. But okay, let's take a
look. אמר רב *Amar Rav* Now we're going to take a look
at this issue about where verbal designation works but drawing lots does
not work. So we'll look at the issue about verbal designation. אמר
רב חסדא. Four lines from the top. אין הקינים מתפרשות Ein hakinim
mitparshot והקינים—the ve-hakinim birds
which as you know talk about a קן kan like a nest,
a pair of birds—are not made explicit, are not designated which is
which, which is the חטאת chatas which is the עולה olah because
as I said they often come in pairs like by a זב
zav or זבה. zava. So אלא או בלקיחת בעלים, ela o bi-lekichat
ba'alim, either at the moment where they're purchased, if the guy's going
to purchase a pair of birds to use for his קרבן korban
he can say at that moment this is an עולה, olah, this
is a חטאת, chatat, או בעשיית הכהן, o be-asiyat ha-kohen,
or when the כהן does it, meaning when the כהן shechts it.
That's normally how we would read ועשאו, ve-asahu, meaning the shechting of
it, the bringing of it as a קרבן. korban.
מליקה Melikah or shechting?
מליקה, Melikah, yeah I used shechting loosely. The מליקה. melikah.
So but if he purchases it—and this is a fascinating idea, this
guy has to bring a קרבן korban or this woman, she purchases
these two birds and she's going to bring it in a week
from now or a day before she goes to the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash she says the gray one is a חטאת, chatat the
white one is an עולה. olah. It doesn't matter. You know, they
were bought without designation, you cannot designate. These have to be designated
now only by the כהן when he actually does the מליקה. melikah.
Now obviously if I said, you know, initially I sanctified this for
this and this for that, but this idea of the two birds
is a fascinating הלכה. halakha. They can be like sanctified as a
pair without being specified, right? You normally couldn't do that. Like you
normally couldn't say I'm going to take these two cows and I'm
going to sanctify them as a חטאת-עולה chatas-olah and I'll sort of
decide which later. You know, if you could do it, it would
be a discussion of יש ברירה, yesh bereira, could you retroactively, but
here they're לכתחילה sort of purchased as a pair and then there's
a moment of designation. So it's so then we can—that could be
at specific moments you're entitled to do that designation and it works
and at other moments not. What were you saying Michael?
I'm sorry, what do you mean by בלקיחת בעלים bi-lekichat ba'alim is
when they purchase it? But that's the same, I can do that
with
any קרבן korban when I purchase it too. So that part's not
the חידוש. chiddush.
That's not the חידוש. chiddush. The חידוש chiddush is if you didn't
do it at the time of purchase, it has to be בעשיית
הכהן. be-asiyat ha-kohen. That is correct. Okay. אמר רב שימי בר אשי.
Amar Rav Shimi bar Ashi. מאי טעמא דרב חסדא? Mai ta'ama de-Rav
Chisda? What's the reasoning of Rav Chisda? דכתיב, De-chtiv, the verse says
ולקחה. ve-lakacha. Okay, so Rashi has the פסוק, pasuk, and ועשה. ve-asa.
There are two פסוקים pesukim which relate to the one being a
חטאת chatat and one being an עולה. olah. So if you look
at Rashi about six lines down in the narrow lines, ולקחה ועשה.
ve-lakacha ve-asa. ביולדת כתיב, Be-yoledet ktiv, ולקחה שתי תורים או שני בני
יונה. ve-lakacha shtei torim o shnei bnei yona. So she shall take.
So when she purchases either the two turtle doves or the two
pigeons, אחד
לעולה ואחד לחטאת, echad le-olah ve-echad le-chatat, and it says she takes
them, one to be an עולה, olah, one to be a חטאת.
Chatat So when she takes them at the moment of purchase, then
they can be designated one as a חטאת, Chatat one as an
עולה. olah. וכן במצורע. Ve-chen be-metzora. וגבי זב, Ve-gabei zav, now by
the זב zav when he brings his two birds it says ועשה
הכהן אחד חטאת ואחד עולה. ve-asah ha-kohen echad chatat ve-echad olah. The
כהן will make one חטאת, Chatat, which suggests that until that moment
it has not yet been determined which is the חטאת, Chatat. which
is the עולה. olah. So those are the two moments that are
significant. By the way, I just came back from Israel and I
was, my
brother-in-law is a tour guide, so we didn't really want a tour,
but when it had snowed we went on like a mini little
hike up a mountain or whatever. And it's near, they had one
of the like near where they live in the ישוב, yishuv, one
of the you know oldest
wine presses, wine or olive oil, olive presses that had been found.
Anyway, but there was also like this,
I forget what they call it, but like this dovecote. You see
this in a lot of these excavations.
Dovecote? Dovecote. Right. But you know it's like this thing in the
ground and it's got like all of these little holes in it,
like all of these little—like שוכין? shochim? Yeah, exactly. So anyway, so
he was pointing out to me that you know, I said so
what is it, why like what was the big deal with pigeons
and doves, why were they so used? He said it required very
little upkeep, you know, you didn't really have to do much to
feed them, and you know, and they could be and they were
a very ready source of meat, and they could be, you know,
and they were inexpensive and you used them regularly for קרבנות. korbanot.
So it's interesting, you know when we think about—think about that often
the קרבן עני korban ani or some of these קרבנות, korbanot, you
know like when you have things that have a very, you know,
have sort of, you know, different levels, you know, and you have
the birds or you often have the birds here by the טהרה
tahara process, I mean just to you know connect that to the
prevalence of how much pigeons and birds and whatever were just a
ready source of like a, you know, of for these קרבנות. korbanot.
It's interesting too that, no no not just קרבנות, korbanot, but the
point is if this was so—the point is it was a very
prevalent and ready source of meat so it was also a way
to bring a live קרבן korban in an inexpensive way. You know,
so yeah.
For the זב zav and the יולדת yoledet or the מצורע, metzora,
these
are their קרבנות korbanot for the טהרה tahara process
that are put together.
Well yeah I mean the question is a lot of these קרבנות
korbanot of the birds, of a חטאת Chatat. and an עולה, olah,
are for the end of a טהרה tahara process, right. Okay, so
let's take a look. או בלקיחה או בעשייה. O bi-lekicha o be-asiyah.
מיתיבי Meitivei says the Gemara, I'll ask you, ועשאו חטאת. ve-asahu chatat.
What?
Nothing in
between.
Yeah, only at those two moments. ועשאו חטאת, ve-asahu chatat, so now
it's going to—now this is going to— ועשהו חטאת, Chatat, so now
it's going to, now this is obviously why we quoted it because
it's going to bring in the ברייתא Baraita we just quoted by
the goats. הגורל עושה חטאת ואין השם עושה חטאת, hagoral oseh chatat
ve'ein hashem oseh chatat, only the lots determine which is the חטאת,
Chatat, not the designation. יכול ולא דין הוא? yachol velo din hu?
I could have made a קל וחומר: kal vachomer:
ומה במקום שלא קידש הגורל uma bimkom shelo kidesh hagoral, קידש השם,
where the lots don't do anything like in the case of the
birds, the designation does something; במקום שקידש הגורל, bimkom shekidesh hagoral, where
the lots does something like by the goats, אינו דין שיקדש השם,
how much more so should verbal designation work? תלמוד לומר ועשהו חטאת,
talmud lomar ve'asahu chatat, הגורל עושה חטאת ואין השם עושה חטאת, hagoral
oseh chatat ve'ein hashem oseh chatat, the גורל makes it into the
חטאת Chatat and not the designation. That was the ברייתא Braita, we
quoted. But now the גמרא Gemara is going to say you're not
comparing like to like because the moment of the הגרלה is not
the moment of the purchase and it's not the moment of the
bringing of the קרבן, korban, of the שחיטה. shechitah. So how can
you make a comparison what works at that moment to the case
of the birds, if at the birds that's not a significant moment?
So that's the גמרא's Gemara. question. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
דהא הכא, deha hacha, in this case of the goats, דלאו שעת
לקיחה ולאו שעת עשייה היא, delav shat lekichah velav shat asiyah hi,
it's not the time of purchase, it's not the time of being
made, meaning the actual שחיטה, shechitah וקתני דקבע, vekatani dekava, and it's
saying that the גורל makes it into a חטאת chatat and it's
contrasting it to the case of the birds, it's assumed to be
the contrast where the verbal designation does it. But the verbal designation
doesn't work at this time by the birds, so what's the comparison?
So אמר רבא, amar Rava, so רבא Rava says הכי קאמר, hachi
ka'amar, this is how you have to read it: ומה במקום שלא
קידש הגורל, what's in the case by birds that the lots do
not designate, ואפילו בשעת לקיחה ואפילו בשעת עשייה, ve'afilu bishat lekichah ve'afilu
bishat asiyah, and even if you would try to do the lots
at the time of purchase or at the time of מליקה melikah
it wouldn't work, so the lots don't work at any stage by
the birds, nevertheless קידש השם בשעת לקיחה ובשעת עשייה, kidesh hashem bishat
lekichah uvishat asiyah, nevertheless a verbal designation works. So by birds, lots
don't work at any stage but a verbal designation does at least
work at two points. Okay, so that's an example where lots never
work but a verbal designation works at those two points. That's by
the birds. So במקום שקידש הגורל, bimkom shekidesh hagoral, where the גורל
does work, שלא בשעת לקיחה ושלא בשעת עשייה, shelo bishat lekichah ushelo
bishat asiyah, in the case of the goats where the גורל does
work, true, not at the time of purchase or the time of
שחיטה, shechitah. but הגורל works at least at some
point. So the argument is, here הגורל doesn't work at all, but
verbal designation does work at these two points. So by the goats
where הגורל works at some stage, then why don't we say that
verbal designation can work at the places where they work with the
birds? Not verbal designation here, but verbal designation at the time of
purchase or at the time of שחיטה. shechitah. How come verbal designation
won't work there if it works in the case of the birds?
And there it's because we have the פסוק pasuk that says the
only thing that works is the lots, not verbal designation.
Then verbal designation would work, what's the point of the הגרלה? You're
saying it's an addition?
Maybe בדיעבד, bedieved, right, or if you didn't do it, meaning exactly
that, to explore that as an alternative.
It was the classic, it was the classic argument where you could
reach a certain conclusion על פי קל וחומר, al pi kal vachomer,
but the פסוק, pasuk, the גמרא's Gemara, more authority. Exactly.
But the way the גמרא Gemara is dealing with this thing, we
weren't trying to get verbal designation to work at the time of
the lots, we are trying to argue that maybe verbal designation should
work like it works by the birds at those two other times.
Okay, תא שמע, ta shma, now that we have pulled in this
discussion, we are going to finish the discussion about the birds even
though this is not directly about עבודת יום הכיפורים. avodat Yom Hakippurim.
תא שמע, ta shma, I heard that.
מטמא מקדש עני, metamei mikdash ani, now one case that somebody can
bring a bird קרבן korban is at the end of ויקרא ה׳,
Vayikra Hei, is some special cases of sins which is a קרבן,
korban, a unique קרבן korban called a קרבן עולה ויורד, korban oleh
veyored, which is a קרבן korban of of going up and down,
of, it could be of, very, it's a scale, like the תורה
Torah charges on a scale. So, on a sliding scale, and based
on if you're rich or if you're poor if you're very poor
do you bring like livestock, do you bring birds, or do you
bring
a מנחה? Mincha? So what are the types of sins that here
so I'll just read you very quickly this is at the end
of פרשת ויקרא. Parshat Vayikra. So it speaks so it says so
here's some the sins that fall into that category. ונפש כי תחטא
ושמעה קול אלה והוא עד או ראה או ידע, Venefesh ki techeta
v'shama kol alah v'hu ed o ra'ah o yada,
so somebody that basically takes an oath that they don't know testimony
and they're lying. אם לוא יגיד ונשא עונו, Im lo yagid v'nasa
avono, so lying about particularly in an oath about testimony. או נפש
אשר תגע בכל דבר טמא או בנבלת חיה טמאה או בנבלת בהמה
טמאה או בנבלת שרץ טמא O nefesh asher tiga b'chol davar tamei
o b'nivlat chayah t'meiah o b'nivlat behemah t'meiah o b'nivlat sheretz tamei
that you are טמא Tamei and ונעלם ממנו V'ne'elam mimenu and it's
hidden from you והוא טמא ואשם V'hu tamei v'ashem and you sin.
So what sin did you do? So חז"ל Chazal understand the sin
is you entered into the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash or you ate
a קרבן. Korban. So that's called טומאת מקדש וקדשיו, Tum'at Mikdash v'Kodashav,
the טומאה Tumah of the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash and of its
sanctified things, its קרבנות. Korbanot. So you did you transgressed the מקדש
Mikdash when you are טמא Tamei without knowing. Okay, and then it
goes, או נפש כי תשבע לבטא בשפתים להרע או להיטיב, O nefesh
ki tishava levate b'sfatayim lehara o lehaitiv, you take a שבועה Shvuah
and you forget about it and you don't do it. So what
do you do? והיה כי יאשם לאחת מאלה והתודה אשר חטא עליה,
V'hayah ki yesham l'achat m'eleh v'hitvadah asher chata aleha, so there's וידוי,
Vidui, והביא את אשמו לה' על חטאתו אשר חטא נקבה מן הצאן.
V'hevi et ashamo l'Hashem al chatato asher chata nekeva min hatzon. You
bring a sheep, a female sheep. ואם לא תגיע ידו די שה
והביא את אשמו אשר חטא שתי תרים או שני בני יונה לה'
אחד לחטאת ואחד לעלה. V'im lo tagia yado dei seh v'hevi et
ashamo asher chata shtei torim o shnei bnei yonah l'Hashem echad l'chatat
v'echad l'olah. Two pigeons or two turtledoves, one for a חטאת chatat
and one for an עולה. Olah. So that's our case. And then
the final case is, ואם לא תשיג ידו לשתי תרים או לשני
בני יונה והביא את קרבנו אשר חטא עשירית האפה סלת לחטאת, V'im
lo tasig yado lishtei torim o lishnei bnei yonah v'hevi et korbano
asher chata asirit ha'eiphah solet l'chatat, right, then you get flour. So
very nice that there's this sliding scale in these cases. So the
גמרא Gemara here deals with that and it picks one of those
sins. It picks the case of טומאת מקדש וקדשיו. Tum'at Mikdash v'Kodashav.
So let's take a look. תא שמע Ta shma says like this,
or מיתיבי, Meitivei, תא שמע, Ta shma, מטמא מקדש
אני, Metamei Mikdash ani, somebody that was מטמא Metamei when they entered
into the מקדש. Mikdash. It's by the way in the context of
יום כיפור Yom Kippur interesting to think about how it frames it.
It's not טמא שנכנס למקדש, Tamei shenichnas l'Mikdash, but מטמא מקדש. Metamei
Mikdash.
You were מטמא Metamei the מקדש. Mikdash. Now obviously you don't take
the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash and put it into the מקווה, Mikvah,
okay, but that sense of the טומאת המקדש Tum'at HaMikdash is a
very major theme of יום כיפור of what the כהן גדול is
doing is cleansing it from the טומאה. Tumah. So מטמא מקדש אני,
Metamei Mikdash ani, now this person was poor and that means would
have brought a bird sacrifice and then he did the sin and
הפריש מעות לקינו Hefrish ma'ot l'kino and he set aside some money
for his pair of birds והעשיר V'he'ashir and then he became rich.
Now the הלכה Halacha is is that if your fortunes change, you
go by what you are when you bring the קרבן. Korban. Or
well it might depend, but at least that's the case here. ואחר
כך אמר, V'achar kach amar, so now he's rich, now he's obligated
in the sheep, not in the birds, but he has this pile
of money and then he says אלו לחטאתו ואלו לעולתו, Elu l'chatato
v'elu l'olato, he splits the pile in half and he says this
half of the pile will be for a חטאת chatat, and this
half of the pile will be for an עולה. Olah. And now
his status has changed and he's in the he's in the sheep
category. So what's the הלכה? Halacha?
So מוסיף ומביא חובתו מדמי חטאתו, Mosif u'mevi chovato midmei chatato, the
pile that he said is for the חטאת, chatat, that can still
be used for the sheep חטאת. chatat, So that half of the
pile add on the extra money that you need to get to
the price of a sheep, which is obviously significantly more than the
price of a bird, and use that money with extra money to
buy your to buy your sheep חטאת. chatat, ואין
מוסיף ומביא חובתו מדמי עולתו, V'ein mosif u'mevi chovato midmei olato, the
pile that half of the pile that he said would be an
עולה, Olah, you can't use that money for your חטאת, chatat you
said it's an עולה Olah and you don't you're not obligated in
an עולה Olah when you're bringing a sheep, a sheep is only
one, it's only the birds that are two. Okay, we'll talk about
later what you do with it, you basically have that money go
to a free an עולה Olah bird that's a נדבה. Nedavah. Okay,
so that's what it says. Okay, that's a pretty straightforward ברייתא, Braita
but let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara So the גמרא
Gemara says one minute, says the גמרא, Gemara דהא הכא D'ha hacha
in this case דלאו שעת לקיחה ולאו שעת עשייה. D'lav shat l'kichah
v'lav shat asiyah. One minute, דלאו שעת לקיחה ולאו שעת עשייה. D'lav
shat l'kichah v'lav shat asiyah. When you're splitting the pile in half,
it's not the time of לקיחה, Lekichah, you didn't purchase the birds
then. Okay, you know what would you would it even work by
money, would you say would designate the money, would you have would
it be only when you purchase the birds? But nevertheless it's some
midpoint, you first set aside the money and then you split it,
so it's not the time of לקיחה Lekichah ולא שעת עשייה, V'lo
shat asiyah, not the time of actual bringing of the קרבן. Korban.
וקתני דקבע, V'katani d'kava, and it sounds like your designation determines which
half is a חטאת, which half is an עולה. Olah. So the
fascinating thing is that the גמרא Gemara could have said that this
is before that that before you actually when you're dealing with money
the story is different before you actually deal with the birds themselves,
you know, but the גמרא Gemara doesn't say that, it assumes that
it works in it works sort of by the same system. So
אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet, רב ששת Rav Sheshet says back
תסברה, Tisperah, one minute, does this ברייתא brayta, make sense anyway? Forget
our issue about when can you designate the חטאת and
the... דאמר רבי אליעזר אמר רבי יהושע, Dehamar Rabbi Eliezer amar Rabbi
Yehoshua, מטמא מקדש עשיר דהביא קרבן
עני, Mitamei Mikdash ashir dehevi korban ani, if somebody was rich when
they were obligated to bring this קרבן korban because they were טמא
tamei and they entered into the מקדש Mikdash and they so they
would have brought a sheep. And then, instead, בדיעבד bedieved he, I
mean not בדיעבד, bedieved
he brought wittingly, unwittingly, it doesn't matter, instead he brought the birds.
He did not bring the sheep. And after he brought that as
a קרבן, korban, בדיעבד bedieved does it work? If you bring a
קרבן korban from a different place on the scale, בדיעבד b'diavad will
it work? Okay, that's the question. So especially if you go lower
on the scale. Yeah, going lower is the problem. גמרא Gemara says
לא יצא. lo yatza. According to רבי יאשיה, Rabbi Yoshiya, you were
not יוצא. yotze. So if that's true, that an עשיר ashir cannot
be יוצא yotze with the קרבן korban of an עני, ani, so
here's the question in this ברייתא, brayta? forgetting about the moment of
designation. כיון דלא יצא, kevan delo yatza, since you're not יוצא, yotze,
היכי קבע? heichi kava? How could it be I sanctified this pile
of money for my bird, now I became rich. If I were
to bring the birds that this money is for, I wouldn't be
יוצא. yotze. So this pile of money is really not relevant to
my קרבן. korban. I'm it's no longer in the category of me
bringing a קרבן korban from this money, this was for the
birds, and it's not relevant. So how could it be, forget what
moment was it, לקיחה, lekicha, עשיה, asiya, once I'm out of the
category, how could any now designation of חטאת and עולה olah be
a meaningful designation since I no longer relate to the sanctity of
this money?
It's not a קל kal anymore. Right.
So any role that I normally could play about designating the money,
I've been taken out of the category.
By the way, that money that had been designated when you were
an עני ani and now you're an עשיר, ashir, is it now
that you're an עשיר ashir it's no longer הקדש? hekdesh?
No, no, it is הקדש, hekdesh, we'll talk about what you do
with it. We'll talk about something else. We'll talk about what you
do with it. But the question is, I don't have a role
of designating it anymore, I've been taken out of the category. So
the גמרא Gemara says, וכיון דלא יצא, vekevan delo yatza, היכי קבע?
heichi kava?
How could you establish what it's used for? אלא
מאי אית לך למימר? ela mai itlach lemeimar? What can you say?
How must you explain this ברייתא? brayta שכבר אמר מעניותו. shekvar amar
meinyutav.
Although the ברייתא brayta says he became rich and then designated, we
must say the ברייתא brayta is being imprecise. And what the ברייתא
brayta means is that you separated the money and then you became
rich. And then it's talking about what you do with it. If
that's how we're already re-reading the ברייתא brayta that it's being imprecise,
so הכא נמי שכבר אמר משעת הפרשה. hacha nami shekvar amar mishat
hafrasha. So once I'm saying it's being imprecise, I'll say that you've
already said which is the חטאת and which is the עולה olah
at the time that you set aside the money and it wasn't
two stages, it was really one stage. Okay, so basically the way
it answers it is by saying it's being imprecise, but it makes
a convincing argument why it's imprecise because you're out of the category.
Now the גמרא Gemara says one minute, but that's only good if
you assume that you are out of the category. ורבי חגא אמר
רבי יאשיה, urabi chaga amar rabbi yoshiya, but רבי חגא Rabbi Chaga
in the name of רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya disagrees with רבי יאשיה.
Rabbi Yoshiya. דאמר יצא. damar yatza. And he says that a rich
person who brought a lesser קרבן korban is יוצא. yotze. So according
to him, you're not out of the category. So we are not
forced to say that the ברייתא brayta. is imprecise. And if that's
true, it really means like it says it means that after you
set aside the money, you're still considered in the category because בדיעבד
if you brought this you'd be יוצא yotze and now you can
establish half for חטאת, half for an עולה, olah, and you're doing
it not at the time of לקיחה lekicha and not at the
time of עשיה. asiya. So we're back to our question. So the
גמרא Gemara says, לא תימא ואחר כך אמר. lo teima veachar kach
amar. So the גמרא gemara says,
okay, but I'm going to give more or less the same answer.
I'm not forced to say it's imprecise, but nevertheless here's how I'm
going to re-read the ברייתא. brayta Don't have it say that after
I set aside the money then I said, אלא אימא ואחר כך
לקח ואמר. ela eima veachar kach lakach veamar.
What I did was, but it's going to be a significant change
of the scenario, because I set aside a pile of money, and
here's what it says. It's not I just said this half of
money is for חטאת, this half is for an עולה. olah. Then
I've got a problem, it's not שעת לקיחה. shat lekicha. What I
did was I took this pile of money, right, I went over
to my good friend Sam here, and I said Sam here, give
me two birds, and then I said this bird is a חטאת,
this bird is an עולה. olah. So that's שעת לקיחה. shat lekicha.
So when the ברייתא brayta said you separated the pile and afterwards
you designated half for חטאת, half for עולה, olah, what's being read
is, yeah, what's the afterwards? When you purchased it you designated. Of
course there's a little bit of a problem, because what does the
ברייתא braisa say you do with the חטאת money?
מוסיף ומביא חובתו,
mosif
umeivi chovato, how do you add money and bring your sheep? But
it's now a bird. What are you supposed to do? So let's
take a look. So the
גמרא gemara says, לקח? lakach? You purchased them? מוסיף ומביא חובתו, mosif
umeivi chovato, how do you add money and bring your sheep? מאי
ניהו? mai niyu? So what would be the only way to explain
that in your scenario? דפרקיה, diparkei, you'd have to redeem the bird,
transfer the קדושה kedusha of the bird onto money and then use
the money. But that's not going to work. ואין פדיון לעוף, vehein
pidyon leoaf, although we know that if a קרבן korban has a
מום, mum, a blemish, you can transfer its value to money and
then use the money to buy another קרבן, korban, חז"ל Chazal understand
that there's no... only buy livestock. It does not apply to birds.
Birds, even if they get a blemish and can't be used, can't
be used, but you can't redeem them. So if you actually already
purchased the bird, how are you going to now use that towards
your קרבן korban, *korban*? So the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says אמר רב
פפא *Amar Rav Pappa*. So רב פפא *Rav Pappa* has a good
answer to this. Let's take a look. כגון שלקח פרידה אחת *Kegon
shelakach preda achas*, אי עולה זבן מוסיף ומביא חובתו *ei olah zavna
mosif umeivi chovaso*. So here's what he says. First I'll explain it
and then we'll read it. I've got my pile of money, okay?
I don't go over to Sam with this whole pile of a
hundred dollars and get what, whatever, ten dollars and get one for
חטאת *chatas* and one for an עולה *olah*. What I do is
I take half the pile, five dollars, and I go to Sam
and I get one bird, okay? Either חטאת *chatas* or an עולה
*olah*. But once I get one bird, that's שעת לקיחה *shat lekicha*
and that automatically therefore
designates the remainder of the pile of money as the other bird.
So actually we can make it into a case of שעת לקיחה
*shat lekicha* and there's still money left over because I only bought
one bird, so that's the time to do the designation, but it
still leaves me with the pile of money that's designated the other
way that I can now add to it and bring the חטאת
*chatas*, okay, and
bring a sheep. Right. So it's been designated for a bird?
Yeah, but apparently that's seen as not that is the חידוש *chiddush*
of this ברייתא braisa *braisa*. That even though it's been sanctified for
a חטאת *chatas*, you know, for a bird for this person, since
it's a חטאת *chatas* for this קרבן korban, *korban* and you're using
it for חטאת *chatas*, that's still... now I do wonder spongeable, I
agree. Now the question is, what if... the question is what if
he was specific? He said, מעות אלו *ma'os eilu* for my two
birds, you know, not just for my... for my קרבן korban *korban*,
for my two birds. Give me one right. So no, but if
at the time that he sanctified the money he specifically made said
for my bird קרבנות *korbanos*, could you still transfer it? I don't
know. Okay, but certainly it's... you can understand it if he was
non-specific: these are for my קרבן korban *korban*. Then his קרבן *korban*
changes. Okay. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says like this: כגון שלקח פרידה אחת *Kegon shelakach preda achas*. You
only bought one bird with half the money. אי עולה זבן *Ei
olah zavna*. If the bird you bought you said was an עולה
*olah*, because then you can designate it at the time of purchase,
so the remainder money is חטאת *chatas* money. So now, again remember,
now you are rich, you can still designate because בדיעבד *bedi'eved* you
could use these for the birds, but now you're rich, so the
leftover money that became חטאת *chatas* money, מוסיף ומביא חובתו מדמי חטאתו
*mosif umeivi chovaso midmei chataso*, add to that money and bring your
חטאת *chatas*. והאי עולה *Veha'i olah*, now what do you do with
the עולה *olah* bird that's been bought? אזלא לנדבה *Azla linderava*... you
just do it as a קרבן נדבה *korban nedava*, a free-will קרבן
*korban*. By the way, we never said what... when we thought the
scenario was just two piles of money, we never said what you
did with the money for the bird, right? Now you actually have
a bird in hand. Oh god.
Okay, but presumably it would be the same thing. Presumably even when
we dealt with two piles of money, the leftover pile that was
for the bird would then be used for a bird נדבה *nedava*.
That's in this... let me just finish the scenario. That's when the
bird... the one you purchased was the עולה *olah*, then you could
add to the leftover money for a חטאת *chatas*. אי חטאת זבן
*Ei chatas zavna*, now if you went ahead and used half the
pile to buy a חטאת *chatas*, so the leftover money is for
the עולה *olah*. So then you are really stuck. אין מוסיף ומביא
חובתו מדמי עולתו *Ein mosif umeivi chovaso midmei olaso*. That's the second
part of the ברייתא braisa. *braisa*. The ברייתא braisa. *braisa* said you
can add to the חטאת *chatas* money but you can't add to
the עולה *olah* money to bring your חטאת *chatas*, to bring your
sheep. So the way he's reading it is those are two scenarios.
If your leftover money was the חטאת *chatas* money and the bird
you bought was an עולה *olah*, then you could add to that
and bring your sheep. If the leftover money was the עולה *olah*
money because the bird you bought you said... you designated a חטאת
*chatas*, then you cannot add... use that money towards your sheep. So
when the ברייתא braisa, *braisa* says what do you do with this
half and that half, he said those are two different scenarios. Okay.
והאי חטאת *Veha'i chatas*, and what do you do with the bird
that's a חטאת *chatas*? So what do you do with a חטאת
*chatas* that you can't bring? אזלא למיתה *Azla lemisa*, so you have
to let it die. Okay. Now that's interesting. I should point out
because since בדיעבד *bedi'eved* we said this is working within the assumption
that בדיעבד *bedi'eved* you could be יוצא yotzei *yotzei*, but nevertheless that's
not considered to be בדיעבד *bedi'eved*, right? בדיעבד *Bedi'avad* means literally the
literal word
בדיעבד *bedi'avad*, post-facto, you've already done it. So this might be now
הלכתית *halachically* we sometimes say שעת הדחק כדיעבד דמי *shas hadchak k'bedi'eved
dami*, but anyway this is not a בדיעבד *bedi'eved* yet, so yes
we're going to... I'm going to go bring my sheep and I
will let have to let that bird die because it cannot be
brought as a קרבן *korban*. Okay. You had a question though.
Just a simple question, what's this word פרידה *preda*? Why does that
refer to the bird?
Yeah, that's just the way in rabbinic terminology a קן *kan* is
referring to the two birds and a פרידה *preda* is one of
the two birds. So פרידה *preda* is a
technical word for one of those two.
Yeah, yeah, I mean I assume they mean like you know a
portion, like
פרידה *prida* is separation, so right it means so one of the
two because you're separating the two, but that's the way it refers
to one, yes. Exactly, it's a technical terminology usage, yep. Okay. So
now, so anyways that was to defend the position that it's only
בשעת לקיחה ובשעת פרישה *bishat lekicha u'bishat prisha*, and we said that
the scenario of leftover money is that you purchased one. And you
have of money being designated as you purchased one and you had
leftover money. גופא, now let's go back to the other to the
other statement we dragged along here about what happens with changing fortunes.
אמר רבי אלעזר אמר רבי הושעיא, Amar Rabbi Elazar amar Rabbi Hoshaya,
נטמא מקדש עשיר והביא קרבן עני, nitmei mikdash ashir v'heivi korban ani,
if the guy was rich when he did the sin and he
brings the lesser קרבן, the birds, לא יצא. lo yatza. So רבי
הושעיא Rabbi Hoshaya says you do not you're not יוצא yotzei if
you go down on the scale. רבי חגא אמר רבי הושעיא Rabbi
Chaga amar Rabbi Hoshaya יצא. yatza. But רבי חגא Rabbi Chaga in
the name of רבי הושעיא, Rabbi Hoshaya, so it's two traditions in
the name of רבי הושעיא, Rabbi Hoshaya, says you are יוצא yotzei.
if you brought lower down on the scale. Now it's interesting we
don't know where they're getting their opinions from, but מיתבי, meisvei, let's
try to clarify. Okay, מצורע עני, metzora ani, we have a ברייתא
braita here in נגעים Negaim by a מצורע. metzora. Somebody that has
these blemishes and מצורע metzora also has a sliding scale. So what
does what's the הלכה halacha there if he takes from a different
position on the scale if he brings? מצורע עני שהביא קרבן עשיר,
Metzora ani she'heivi korban ashir, if he's poor and he goes up
on the scale, he brings the richer
קרבן, יצא, yatza, ברייתא says you're יוצא. yotzei. עשיר שהביא קרבן עני,
Ashir she'heivi korban ani, if you're rich and you buy bring from
the lower point on the scale, לא יצא, lo yatza, you're not
יוצא. yotzei, So what do you see? Presumably it's all the same
הלכה, halacha, right? I mean yes it's different categories in the תורה,
Torah, one is קרבן עולה ויורד, korban oleh v'yored, the other is
מצורע, metzora, but they both have the same idea of a sliding
scale. And this clarifies the הלכה. halacha. And you see there you
see there by a מצורע metzora to go down on the scale
is no good. So how could there what's the how do you
defend yourself the tradition of רבי הושעיא Rabbi Hoshaya that says if
you go down on the scale it is kosher? Not by a
מצורע metzora but by the case of of other קרבן עולה ויורד.
korban oleh v'yored. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. So
obviously the goal would be to say that מצורע metzora is a
different category. Or say this
is a מחלוקת machlokes on this. No but it's רבי הושעיא, Rabbi
Hoshaya, this is a משנה mishna and those are right אמוראי. Amorai.
Yeah but they have
another תנא Tanna who follows them. פשיטא. Pshita. שאני התם, Shani hatam,
no so we're going to say מצורע metzora is an exception. There
it's different. דכתיב, d'ksiv, the verse says זאת, Zos, זאת תהיה תורת
המצורע ביום טהרתו. zos tihyeh toras hametzora b'yom taharaso. This, meaning it
has to be exactly the way it is and you can't you
know you can't fool around so it's exactly the way it's supposed
it's set up. אי הכי, ei hachi, if that's it that everything
has to be precise so רישא נמי? reisha nami? How about going
up on the scale? The first half of that משנה, mishna, right?
So you're so it says if you go up on the scale
you are יוצא, yotzei. that's not precise. So it says הא ריבה
רחמנא תורת. ha ribah rachmana toras. No cause it says זאת תהיה
תורת zos tihyeh toras המצורע. hametzora. תורת toras means a category which
means that it's more inclusive. So one word is exclusive and one
word is inclusive. So we make a logical you know assignment you
know which is that going down going up is better than going
down.
More benefit to the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. Well yeah but also logically the תורה Torah wants to
go easy on you. You're only entitled for the sort of lower
scale if you're entitled for it you know but if you want
to bring you know do more כל הכבוד. kol hakavod. So that's
what we say by מצורע. metzora. So by מצורע metzora you can
only go up and you can't go down if it's down it's
no good because of the word זאת. zos. But what רבי הושעיא
Rabbi Hoshaya would say, but by we don't have that word זאת
zos by the case of קרבן עולה ויורד. korban oleh v'yored. And
there בדיעבד even if you went down you would still be יוצא.
yotzei. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי רישא נמי הא
ריבה רחמנא תורת. ei hachi reisha nami ha ribah rachmana toras. I'm
sorry. והתניא. V'hatanya. And we taught the same in a ברייתא. והתניא
V'hatanya sometimes is a word to introduce a challenge but sometimes it's
a word to introduce a you know a support and we taught
just like this in the ברייתא. תורת לרבות מצורע עני שהביא קרבן
עשיר. Toras l'rabos metzora ani she'heivi korban ashir. The word תורת Toras
says that you don't have to be precise if you're poor and
you bring the קרבן of a rich person you're יוצא. yotzei, יכול
אפילו עשיר שהביא קרבן עני, Yachol afilu ashir she'heivi korban ani, maybe
even if you went down on the scale you'd be יוצא, yotzei.
תלמוד לומר זאת. talmud lomar zos. So it says זאת, zos, so
exactly what we said is in the ברייתא, that's where you get
it by a מצורע, metzora, but it's only by a מצורע. metzora.
So now the גמרא Gemara says ונילף מינה, v'neilaf minah, why is
it only by מצורע? metzora? Let's use this as a paradigm, let's
apply this same principle to our case. So why here does is
there a version of רבי הושעיא Rabbi Hoshaya that says you are
allowed to go down? דמיעט רחמנא ואם דל הוא. d'miat rachmana v'im
dal hu. So the word ואם דל הוא, v'im dal hu, if
he, that's the word הוא hu is seen as extra is seen
to sort of be pointing a finger so it's seems to be
saying like wait a minute where does that say? That's by the
מצורע, metzora, that's not by the עולה ויורד. oleh v'yored. So it
says הוא, hu, by this case, by the מצורע metzora case, a
poor person if he goes you know you have to be have
this type of precision and if you're rich and you bring the
קרבן of a poor person you're not יוצא. But רבי הושעיא Rabbi
Hoshaya would say in the case of a קרבן עולה ויורד korban
oleh v'yored we are not as precise. So we have more words
by מצורע, metzora, we have a word that sort of that tells
me you can go up and not down. תורת says you can
go up, זאת zos tells me you can't go down. Why don't
I apply that to other cases? Because the other word by מצורע
metzora is ואם דל הוא, v'im dal hu, which is saying here
is where by this case this person is where these principles apply,
these principles do not are not meant to apply elsewhere.
Isn't that by all cases of קרבן עולה ויורד? korban oleh v'yored?
ואם דל הוא v'im dal hu is just by the מצורע? metzora?
I thought...
Yeah but we use it by the מצורע metzora to tell me
don't apply whatever principles you have here to anything else. I don't
know, no. Whatever. I mean what, that פסוק pasuk is by the
מצורע. metzora. You know, Michael, this gets to the larger question, חז"ל,
Chazal, okay, about whether how much is it sort of things that
they knew and that they're finding the link in the פסוק pasuk
and how much is it really open-ended and they're deriving it from
the פסוק. pasuk.
Unusual for הא דתניא Ha detanya to be support.
Unusual but not, but not rare, I mean there are many cases
of it. There are many cases of it. Okay. So now we
get to go back to the עבודה. Let's take a look. Now,
קשר לשון של זהורית בראש שעיר המשתלח.
kasher lashon shel zehorit
berosh se'ir hamishtale'ach. So where are we, by the way?
In the משנה, mishnah, דף, daf, oh, wait, we have to look
at סדר העבודה Seder Ha'avodah again, but let's get back to the
visuals for a moment.
Okay, so here is your קודש הקודשים. Kodesh Hakodashim. What?
Here's
the קודש. kodesh.
Yeah,
I know.
I know how it ends.
רש"י Rashi says it best. Okay, anyway, alright.
So anyway, מנורה, menorah, שולחן, shulchan, מזבח, mizbe'ach, אולם, ulam,
okay,
here's your עזרה, azarah, right?
Here's your מזבח. mizbe'ach. Now, what did we say? Let's review what's
been happening. Okay, step number one is he do the פר, par,
and that's בין האולם ולמזבח. bein ha'ulam velamizbe'ach. There's the whole discussion
of is the space בין האולם ולמזבח bein ha'ulam velamizbe'ach in the
north or not? Right? Is the whole thing in the south, is
it in the north? But let's assume that it's in the north.
Let's assume this is the line between north and south. So here
he is with the cow in האולם ולמזבח, ha'ulam velamizbe'ach, he does
the וידוי. viduy. Okay, that's step number one. That's פר. par. How'd
they get him to turn his head? Whatever. Now he walks over
here and it says, it says to the north of the מזבח
mizbe'ach is where he's doing the thing with the goats. Okay, here
are the two goats, right? Here's a lot. להשם, l'Hashem, whatever, okay,
here he is, he's down. So that's what he's done now, he's
done the things he's designated. So that's where we are, up to
stage number two, which is the שעירים. se'irim. Okay, so the last
thing we had read was that he drew the lots and that
he designated right hand, left hand, the whole thing. Now we're going
to do some more. Here alone? Anyone else? Well, there's the סגן,
there's the אב בית דין, av beit din, remember so they were
there. And presumably there were a lot of people that were watching
the עבודה. As ישעיה Yeshayah said to that three-way מחלוקת machlokes or
earlier a few דפים dafim ago like where's צפון? tzafon? Added areas
you could add, like specifically more. Exactly, could he have done it
here? Could he have done it here? I'm just keeping to the
language of the משנה. mishnah. By the way, the whole thing וכל
אדם לא יהיה באהל מועד vechol adam lo yiyeh be'ohel mo'ed is
this area. This is the only area that he has to be
alone. Okay, this is the אהל מועד ohel mo'ed is the היכל.
heichal. Right, that's the, that's the אהל מועד ohel mo'ed in the
תורה, Torah, right? Okay, this thing is the אולם ulam which does
not have a counterpart in the תורה Torah and this is the
open-air space is the עזרה. azarah. Okay, remember, yes, there's discussion whether
the altar outside was below the, yes, I'm following the משנה mishnah
which, I'm just going by the משנה, mishnah, I know the גמרא
sort of, you know, that was the whole discussion in the earlier
דפים, dafim, but in the משנה mishnah he was בין האולם ולמזבח
bein ha'ulam velamizbe'ach and still in the north. So that assumes that
the altar was partly in the north. Okay, yes, according to another
version he was in the space beyond, he was here, he wasn't
actually here. That was the discussion you had a few days ago.
Okay, so let's take a look. קשר לשון של זהורית בראש שעיר
המשתלח, kasher lashon shel zehorit berosh se'ir hamishtale'ach, so he puts the
red thing of the red string, he tied it to the head
of the animal that's to be sent over the cliff. You know,
you normally assume it means the horns, but it doesn't say the
horns, it just says tied it on the head. So he tied
it around the neck, but we'll get to more of that later.
והעמידו כנגד בית שילוחו, ve'he'emido keneged beit shilucho, and then he took
that goat and put it opposite where the gate from where it
would be sent away. Okay, so we'll discuss later where exactly that
gate was, but he put it, that goat went and was taken
away, whether he took it or other people then took it, but
it was placed now ready to be sent away by the door
that it would leave from. ולנשחט, velanishchat, the one that's going to
be שחט׳ד, shechted, interesting that it calls it ולנשחט, velanishchat, doesn't call
it the one that's להשם, l'Hashem, but you know, anyway, that's going
to be the next stage, the שחיטה-ing it. And also ties in
to what we're doing with it. ולנשחט כנגד בית שחיטתו, velanishchat keneged
beit shechitato, you put it opposite the house of שחיטה.
Now what exactly that means, we will talk about.
The simple sense of reading it presumably would mean you put it
in the place where you're going to do the שחיטה.
Okay, but we'll see how the גמרא interprets it. Okay, so that's
it. He's got those two animals ready, one ready to be sent
away, the other ready to be שחט׳ד. shechted. בא לו אצל פרו
שניה, ba lo etzel paro sheniyah, then he comes back to his
cow. וסמך שתי ידיו עליו ומתודה, vesamach shtei yadav alav umitvaddeh, he
puts his hands on it and he says the וידוי. viduy. וכך
היה אומר, vekach hayah omer, okay, this is what he would say:
אנא
השם חטאתי עויתי
פשעתי,
ana Hashem chatati
aviti pashati, right?
Or actually if you look at the side the גרסא girsa in
the משנה mishnah because remember the גמרא had a whole question.
which is the
order so the משנה Mishnah is עויתי פשעתי חטאתי Aviti pashati chatati
which reflects the לשון lashon in the פסוקים pesukim לפניך אני וביתי
lifanecha ani uvaiti ובני אהרן uvenei Aharon now he's not only me
and my immediate household but all of the כהנים kohanim because this
is for him
and for the כהנים kohanim עם קדשך am kadshecha אנא השם כפר
נא לעונות ולפשעים ולחטאים Ana Hashem kaper na la'avonot v'l'pashaim v'l'chataim that's
you see follows the עויתי פשעתי חטאתי aviti pashati chatati שעויתי ושפשעתי
ושחטאתי לפניך אני וביתי ובני אהרן עם קדשך she'aviti v'shepashati v'shechatati lifanecha
ani uvaiti uvenei Aharon am kadshecha ככתוב בתורת משה עבדך kakatuv b'torat
Moshe avdecha they get this straight from the מחזור machzor כי ביום
הזה יכפר עליכם לטהר אתכם מכל חטאתיכם לפני השם תטהרו ki vayom
hazeh yechaper aleichem letaher etchem mikol chatoteichem lifnei Hashem titharu by the
way מכל חטאתיכם mikol chatoteichem goes on the second half of the
פסוק pasuk it's not לטהר אתכם מכל חטאתיכם letaher etchem mikol chatoteichem
לטהר אתכם letaher etchem period מכל חטאתיכם לפני השם תטהרו mikol chatoteichem
lifnei Hashem titharu והם עונים אחריו ברוך שם כבוד מלכותו לעולם ועד
v'hem onim acharav Baruch shem kvod malchuto l'olam va'ed so we've seen
that already so now after step number two he goes back here
for step number three and does it again but this time it
is also with for all of the כהנים so the תטהרו titharu
is reflexive תטהרו titharu yes והם עונים אחריו v'hem onim acharav is
everybody everybody who's in the עזרה azarah like I said there's a
lot of people like they could be filled the עזרה azarah they're
there to watch the ceremony okay איבעיא להו ibaia lehu so they
ask the question ולאנשחט v'lanishchat when it says that for the נשחט
nishchat you do it you know כנגד בית שחיטתו k'neged beit shechitatu
how do you read that line does it mean ולאנשחט אקשירה קאי
v'lanishchat akshira kai does it mean you tie the red string to
the head of the goat that's going to be sent away and
you tie a red string to the one that will be שחט
shechted opposite where it will be שחט shechted which would mean around
its neck so maybe when it says what you do to the
one that'll be שחט shechted it's not talking about where you place
it it goes back to the first verb it goes back to
the tying of a red string או אהמדה קאי o ahamada kai
or is it saying the second verb you placed the one that's
going to be sent in one place and you placed the one
that's going to be שחט shechted in another place so it really
seems like the latter you know because that was the most proximate
verb but let's see what the גמרא says תא שמע ta shema
come and hear דתני רב יוסף d'tanei Rav Yosef רב יוסף Rav
Yosef has a ברייתא קשר לשון של זהורית בראש שעיר המשתלח kashar
lashon shel zehorit b'rosh sa'ir hamishtaleach you would tie a red string
to the head of the goat that will be sent away notice
again by the way it said head not horns okay והעמידו כנגד
בית שילוחו v'he'emido k'neged beit shillucho and you stand it opposite where
it's going to be sent away from ולאנשחט כנגד בית שחיטתו v'lanishchat
k'neged beit shechitatu and the one that will be שחט shechted where
it will be שחט shechted so from now again it's still the
same ambiguity do you tie a red string where it'll be שחט
shechted or do you place it where it'll be שחט shechted so
now the but we're going to learn from the next statement שלא
יתערב זה בזה shelo yitarev zeh b'zeh so the two goats should
not be mixed up one to the other ולא יתערב באחרים v'lo
yitarev b'acherim and should not be mixed up with other goats now
I have to say I don't begin to understand other goats what
other goats are walking around in the עזרה azarah unless unless maybe
the concern is that when you're when you're taking the goat out
like let's say and you're racing it off the cliff let's say
a herd of goats comes by and it gets mixed up and
you so that could be a scenario okay so the גמרא says
like this אי אמרת אקשירה קאי ei amart akshira kai if it's
saying that you tie a red string around its neck where it
will be שחט shechted from okay so שפיר shapir now I understand
that the red strings separate them from one another now the way
they would separate them from one another would presumably be because the
red string on the goat sent away would be between its horns
and the red string on the one to be שחט shechted would
be on its neck they use the same thing that's like use
a color for milkics and fleishics this is the same color no
no it's very easy you just designate M for milkics and M
for meat so there you go so anyway okay so anyway if
they both have red strings and the red strings are in different
places the one for the goat to be sent off the cliff
would be between the horns and the one for the goat to
be שחט shechted would be on its neck then they're they're separate
from one another and they're separate from other animals so then so
אי אמרת אקשירה קאי ei amart akshira kai so they both have
strings שפיר shapir now we get it אלא אי אמרת אהמדה קאי
ela ei amart ahamada kai but if only the one has the
red string and when it talks about the one you're going to
שחט shecht it's not a string it's just talking about where you
stand it where you place it so I don't get it נהי
דבחבריה לא מיערב nehi d'bachavreih lo mi'arev I get how it won't
get mixed up with the other goat because the other one has
a string and this doesn't בהאי קטר ביה ובהאי לא קטר ביה
b'hai katar beih uv'hai lo katar beih the one that's going off
the cliff has it has a string tied on it and this
does not ובאחרני ממיערב uv'achrinei mi mi'arev but this could still get
mixed up with others so how do you say that we have
now prevented them from getting mixed up with others you haven't prevented
this one you've just placed it somewhere אלא לאו שמע מינה אקשירה
קאי ela lav shma mina akshira kai so it must be when
it says that the one will be שחט shechted you do it
where it'll be שחט shechted it doesn't mean you place it at
the place it'll be שחט shechted it means you put a string
around its neck from where it will be שחט shechted שמע מינה
shma mina and the גמרא actually concludes this way so who ever
heard of this right did you know this you've been saying the
עבודה the entire your entire lives all of a sudden we find
out that there's also a red string around the one you're going
to שחט shecht around its neck and that seems to be how
the גמרא concludes but it is interesting that that does not seem
to be reflected I don't know about all of the I don't
know about all the various פיוטים *piyutim* for the עבודה *Avodah*—but it
does not seem to be reflected, you know, in מחזור *Machzor*-related literature.
And by the way, the ברייתא *Braita* is not hard to understand.
The only one like I said before that you have to keep—that
you have to make clear doesn't get mixed up with others, is
the one you're sending away, because then it actually might encounter some
other goats on its trip to the cliff. The one that stayed
in the עזרה *Azara*'s not going to encounter any other goats, so
you don't really need to keep that one separate from others. But
this is the way the גמרא *Gemara*'s reading the ברייתא *Braita* that
there was a red string on the horns of the one to
be sent over, and a red string around the neck of the
one that was going to be שחט *shecht*ed. Okay, now let's move
on to אמר רבי יצחק *Amar Rabbi Yitzchak*, so we're going to
still be dealing with this string. שתי לשונות שמעתי *Shtei leshonot shamati*.
I heard about two strings. אחת של פרה *Achat shel parah*, one
of the פרה אדומה *Parah Adumah* because the תורה *Torah* says by
the פרה אדומה *Parah Adumah*, when you're burning the פרה *parah* it
says you throw into it עץ ארז ואזוב *etz erez ve'ezov*, right,
a piece of cedar and a hyssop, ושני תולעת *ushni tola'at*, and
a red string. So that's another red string. Okay, the red string
by the way of the goat being sent off is nowhere in
the תורה *Torah*, right? I mean plus like this whole very big
symbolism but that's, you know, not in the תורה *Torah*. Okay, anyway,
שני תולעת *shni tola'at*, I thought was, you know, to deepen the
red color along with the אזוב *ezov*. No, it's understood to be
a separate red string. Okay, but for—I thought there for the purposes
of deepening—I don't know what the purpose is. It's one of the
things you throw into the fire. So let's take a look. Okay,
אחת של פרה ואחת של שעיר המשתלח *Achat shel parah ve'achat shel
sair hamishtaleach*. אחת צריכה שיעור *Achat tzericha shiur*, one has a minimum
size, ואחת אינה צריכה שיעור *ve'achat einah tzericha shiur*, and the other
does not have a minimum size. ולא ידנא הי מינייהו *Velo yadana
he minayhu*, I don't know which is which. אמר רב יוסף *Amar
Rav Yosef*, נחזי אנן *nechezi anan*, let's figure it out. Let's take
a look ourselves. של שעיר המשתלח דבעי חלוקה בעי שיעור *Shel sair
hamishtaleach deba'i chaluka ba'i shiur*, the one you're going to send over
the cliff, it's not enough to tie it between the horns because
we're going to find out later that you split it. You keep
half and you keep the other half around the horn so you
can see that remaining half turning white. So that one, you actually
need a minimum, meaning it has to—it's not just practically what connects
to the horns. And of course you could say, okay, but again,
it's not a formal number, it's just enough to do the job.
But that's considered to be—translates into a minimum. Okay? In order to
be able to achieve both, to have it between the horns and
have a half left over. ושל פרה דלא בעי חלוקה לא בעי
שיעור *Veshel parah delo ba'i chaluka lo ba'i shiur*, the one of
the פרה *parah* that you're not going to split in half doesn't
have a minimum, any tiny string will be fine. מתקי לה רמי
בר חמא *Matkei lah Rami bar Chama*, so רמי בר חמא *Rami
bar Chama* asks on this, דפרה נמי בעי כובד *deparah nami ba'i
koved*, one minute, the פרה *parah* needs to have—when you throw it
in the fire, if it doesn't have weight to it, it's going
to like flutter away. So it needs a minimum, not necessarily a
minimum length, but maybe a minimum weight. There might be some minimum
quantity. Yeah, you need some weight to it in order for it
to fall into the fire. והשליך *Vehishlich*, it says you cast it
in the fire. If I threw it and it like fluttered into
the fire like this, that's not והשליך *vehishlich*, that's not to cast
it in the fire. So it would need a minimum too. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says we'll read just more—one more line. אמר ליה
רבא *Amar leh Rava*, כובד תנאי היא *koved tanna'i hi*. Okay, the
idea of whether you need weight for the—for the string, whether the
string has to fall or can it flutter by the פרה אדומה
*Parah Adumah*, we're going to see later tomorrow is a debate of
תנאים *Tanna'im*. So according to the תנא *Tanna* that says it doesn't
have to have weight,
a
lot
of weight, it can flutter in, according to that approach, we would
understand that the פרה אדומה *Parah Adumah* does not have a minimum
size or minimum weight, the tiniest amount that would flutter in, that's
fine, but the goat does have a minimum at least in length
because you need amount between the horns and you need another amount
to preserve. What we're going to see tomorrow is a whole range
of different opinions about which one has a minimum and other red
strings and how they fit into this question about minimum size or
minimum weight.